Guide to the Barbara Newhall Follett Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Barbara Newhall Follett Papers,
1919-1966
[Bulk Dates: 1919-1939]
Follett, Barbara Newhall, 1914-1966
2.73 linear feet (6.5 document boxes)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library New York, NY. 10027
MS#0439
4078771
Barbara Newhall Follett’s papers consist primarily of personal letters, manuscripts of published and unpublished books, short stories, essays, and poems, book reviews, newspaper clippings, photographs, and notes written by her mother, Helen Follett.
Biographical Note
Barbara Newhall Follett was born on March 4, 1914. Her parents were Wilson Follett, an English professor and a writer, and Helen Thomas Follett, also a writer. Barbara was homeschooled by her mother, who believed that children should learn at their own pace. At the age of five, Barbara started to use the typewriter and learned how to make new words and form sentences. She also began to write letters to relatives and friends.
During her childhood years, she wrote numerous short stories, essays, and poems about nature. Barbara had a vivid imagination and created a make-believe world called Farksolia, in which she also developed its language and vocabulary.
Her first book, House Without Windows, was published in 1927, when she was thirteen years old. It was critically acclaimed and she wrote another book, The Voyage of the Norman D, that was published the following year, She was hailed as a "child genius" and "a child prodigy author" by newspapers around the country. She made the headlines again when she and her mother went on a long sailing voyage to the Caribbean and the South Seas Islands during the late 1920s. They co-authored a book about their trip together and it was published in 1932 as Magic Portholes.
After her father left the family in 1928, Ms. Follett and her mother had to find a way of bringing in steady income between their writing assignments. Starting at sixteen years of age, she worked as a typist in New York City while living with her mother. From her late teens to her early twenties, she traveled extensively in the U.S. and Europe with her boyfriend and then husband, Nickerson Rogers.
On December 7, 1939, after an argument with her husband, Barbara Follett left their apartment with only a few dollars. She was never seen or heard from again. She was twenty-five years old.
Scope and Content
Barbara Follett's papers primarily consist of personal letters, manuscripts of published and unpublished works, photographs, newspaper clippings, and research materials relating to her autobiography that was published in 1965.
The correspondence was originally processed by year and the current arrangement reflects this order. Select letters were also catalogued and arranged by special friends of Ms. Follett.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in five series:
Series I: Correspondence, 1919-1952
Series II: Published Materials, 1927-1968
Series III: Unpublished Materials, 1919-1934
Series IV: Childhood Materials, 1922-1925
Series V: Barbara's Autobiography, 1960-1966
Subjects
Follett, Barbara Newhall 1914-1939; Follet, Helen Thomas; Follett, Wilson, 1887-1963
Access Restrictions
This collection is located on-site.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
Follett, Helen Thomas Bequest 1970 M-70
Selected Related Material-- at Columbia
Helen Thomas Follett Papers, Rare Book & Manuscript Library.
Finding aid in repository; folder level control.
- Series I: Correspondence, 1919-1952
  This series consists primarily of personal letters from Barbara Follett to Mr. Oberg; Alice Dyer Russell, a very close friend; and to her mother, Helen Follett.
  - Letters from Barbara Follett to Relatives and Friends, 1919-1939, (11 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 1 to 11)
  - Letters to Barbara Follett, 1918-1935 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Letters from Mr. Oberg to Barbara Follett, 1919-1932 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Letters from George Bryan to Barbara Follett, 1926-1928 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Letters from de la Mare, Walter, 1925-1927 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - January 6, 1925
    - January 6, 1926
    - March 21, 1927
  - Letters from Farjeon, Harry, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - May 9, 1927
    - July, 31, 1927
  - Letter from Hall, Norman, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - August 27, 1928
  - Letters from Knopf, Blanche (Mrs. Alfred), 1926 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - April 14, 1926
    - November 18, 1927
  - Letter from Mencken, Henry Louis, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Letter from Perkins, Frances, June 20, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Letters regarding Barbara’s Disappearance, 1949-1952 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Letters from Barbara Follett, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Series II: Published Materials, 1927-1933
  In this series, the papers are published manuscripts in various versions. The titles are: House Without Windows; I n Defense of Butterflies; and The Voyage of the Norman D.
  - House Without Windows, 1927
    - Manuscript with Corrections, 1927 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Galley Proofs, 1927 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Book Reviews, 1927-1968 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - "I’ve Got to Go to Sea Again" Article, Young Wings Magazine, June 1932 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - In Defense of Butterflies, 1933
    - Manuscript, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Printed article in The Horn Book Magazine, February 1933 (Box 3, Folder  6)
  - Sail of Gold Book Review, 1927 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - The Voyage of Norman D., 1927-1928
    - Original Manuscript, 1927 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Manuscript with edits, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Author’s Proofs, 1928 (2 Folders) (Box 3, Folder 10 to 11)
    - Book Reviews, 1928 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Series III: Unpublished Materials, 1919-1934
  This series contains unpublished manuscripts of books, short stories, essays, and poems.
  - Lost Island, 1932-1934 (Box 4)
    - Manuscript, Chapters I - XVIII, 1934 (2 Folders) (Box 4, Folder 1 to 2)
    - Manuscript Carbon Copy, Chapters I - XVI, 1932 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Short Draft of Manuscript, 103 pages, 1932 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Travel Without a Donkey Manuscript, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Short Stories and Essays, 1919-1920s (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Short Stories (Early Years), 1921-1923 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Short Stories, undated, (3 Folders) (Box 5, Folder 2 to 4)
  - Poems and Prose, 1919-1927 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Christmas Poem and Song, 1924-1925 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Photocopies of Barbara’s Writings, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Descriptions of European Trip, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Series IV: Childhood Materials, 1922-1925
  These files contain materials related to Barbara’s education at home, notes and history of Farksoo, a make-believe land; butterfly drawings; and numerous notes about Barbara’s interest in nature from her mother.
  - History of Farksolia, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Notes about Farksolia, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Farksoo Language and Vocabulary,undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Home Schooling including Diary, 1920-1924 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Notes about Barbara’s Love for Nature, circa 1920s (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Wilson Follett Articles On a Child Author, 1919 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Arts & Crafts, circa 1919-1920s (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Butterfly Illustrations by Mr. Oberg Specified by Barbara, undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Series V: Barbara’s Autobiography, 1919-1966
  In this series, there is correspondence between Helen Follett and the writer, Mr. McCurdy, a professor of psychology; research materials about Barbara’s life; photographs, and copies of her writings.
  - Correspondence between Helen Follett and Mr. McCurdy, 1960-1966 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Autobiography Manuscript, 1961-1965 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Timeline and Notes of Barbara’s Letters and Writings, 1919-1939 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Legal Records (House Without Windows Contract and Legal Divorce Papers), 1926-1944 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Photographs, 1920-1929 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - A Copy of the Book, Barbara: The Unconscious Autobiography of a Child Genius, 1966 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Book Reviews, 1966 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Nickerson Rogers Papers, 1949-1958 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Copies of Newspaper Clippings, 1966 (Box 7, Folder 9)